Seeing is not believing.
眼见并不为实
Our senses can deceive us.
我们的感官会误导我们
Even the stars are not what they appear to be.
这些星星并不是我们看到的样子
The cosmos, as revealed by science,
通过科学展示出的宇宙
is stranger than we ever could have imagined.
比我们所能想象的更离奇
Light and time and space and gravity
光 时间 空间 万有引力
conspire to create realities
共同创造出
which lie beyond human experience.
我们从未体验过的现实
That's where we're headed.
让我们一探究竟
Come with me.
跟我来
Back in 1802, on a night like this,
1802年 像这样的一个夜晚
the astronomer William Herschel strolled the beach
天文学家威廉·赫歇尔和他的儿子
on the English coast, with his son John.
在英国海边散步
Herschel was the first person ever
赫歇尔（恒星天文学之父）是有史以来第一位
to see into the deeper waters of the cosmic ocean.
看穿宇宙深层奥秘的人
There he glimpsed the magic trick
他看穿了光线和时间
that light does with time.
一起变出的戏法
Father...
父亲
do you believe in ghosts?
你相信有鬼魂吗
Why, yes, my son!
怎么了  我相信
You, you do?
你信
I would not have thought so.
我真没想到
Oh, no, not in the human kind of ghost.
哦,不,不是人死后的鬼魂
No... not at all.
绝不是那种
But look up, my boy,
抬头看 儿子
and see a sky full of them.
天空中满是鬼魂
The stars, Father?
星星  父亲
I do not follow.
我没听懂
Every star is a sun as big, as bright as our own.
每个星星都像我们的太阳那么亮 那么大
Just imagine how far away from
us you'd have to move the Sun
想想看要把太阳移到多远以外
to make it appear as small and faint as a star.
才能让它看上去像星星那样小
The light from the stars travels very fast...
星星发出的光 速度很快
faster than anything...
最快的速度
but not infinitely fast.
但并不是无限的快
It takes time for their light to reach us.
星光到达我们这里需要时间
For the nearest ones, it takes years.
最近的可能需要几年
For others, centuries.
其他那些  几百年
Some stars are so far away,
还有一些特别远的
it takes eons for their light to get to Earth.
需要亿万年才能到达地球
By the time the light from some stars gets here,
等那些星星发出的光到达这里
they are already dead.
星星已经死了
For those stars, we see only their ghosts.
对这些星星来说  我们看到的只是它们的鬼魂
We see their light,
我们看到它们的光
but their bodies perished long, long ago.
但它们的星球已经死了很久很久
John, I have seen further back in time
约翰  我比我们的古人
than any man before me--
能看到更古老的过去
millions of years into the past.
几百万年前的过去
William Herschel was the first person to understand
威廉·赫歇尔是第一个认识到
that a telescope is a time machine.
望远镜就是一个时间机器
We cannot look out into space
我们看向太空
without seeing back in time.
就是看向过去
In one second, light travels 300,000 kilometers,
一秒钟  光穿越30万公里
or 186,000 miles.
或者18万6千英里
That's nearly the distance from the Earth to the Moon.
几乎就是地球到月亮的距离
So, the Moon is about one light-second away.
所以月亮离我们1光秒
The next time you look at the Moon,
下次你看向月亮
you'll be seeing one second into the past.
你就会看到1秒钟以前的过去
Sync and corrections by n17t01
www.addic7ed.com
中文翻译 @SaltyEggPain
宇    宙
时空探险之旅
第 4 集
遍布鬼魂的天空
A Sky Full of Ghosts
That Sun...
太阳
it's not really there.
并不真的在那个位置
It won't actually be above the horizon
太阳实际上升出地平线
for another two minutes.
是两分钟以后的事情
The sunrise is an illusion.
日出只是个幻象
Earth's atmosphere bends the incoming rays of sunlight
大气层使射入的阳光发生了折射
like a lens or a glass of water.
就像镜片和一杯水那样
So we see the image of the Sun
projected above the horizon...
所以我们看到的只是地平线之上的投影
before the physical Sun is actually there.
太阳本身还没到达那个位置
That Sun behind me is a mirage.
我身后的太阳只是海市蜃楼
No more real than the shimmering image
就像那闪烁的图像
that hovers in the distance
漂浮在
over a desert road on a hot day.
炎热天气下的沙漠远方
Sunlight takes about eight minutes to reach Earth,
日光需要8分钟才能达到地球
so the Sun is eight light-minutes away.
太阳离我们8光分
From Earth, we can only ever see the Sun
对于太阳来说  我们只能看到它
as it was eight minutes ago.
8分钟之前的样子
And another thing,
还有一件事
the Sun doesn't really "rise" at all.
太阳并不是真的 升起
The Earth turns and we turn with it.
地球带着我们一起旋转
It may not look like it,
but right at this moment,
看上去也许不像  但是这个时候
I'm moving faster than a jet plane
我比飞机走的还快
and so are you and everyone on Earth.
你也是  其他所有人都一样
While I'm at it,
当我看过去
that horizon...
地平线
it's not really there at all.
并不真的存在
There's no edge.
根本没有边缘
The horizon is just another illusion.
地平线也是一种幻象
The distance between Earth
地球离
and the outermost planet Neptune
最外围的行星  海王星的距离
varies as the planets orbit the Sun.
随着环日轨道而不同
On average, the light makes that trip in four hours.
平均来说  光要4个小时才能传来
So for us on Earth,
所以对我们来说
the Neptune we see is always four hours in the past--
我们看到的是4小时前海王星的样子
four light-hours away.
距离 4光时
But the distances to the planets,
但行星间的距离
even the farthest one...
就算最遥远的
are mere baby steps on a much grander scale
也只不过是微不足道的
of the stars and galaxies.
相对星系间和恒星间的距离来说
As soon as we leave the Sun's
immediate neighborhood,
一旦我们离开太阳系
we need to change the unitive distance
我们就需要把距离单位
from light-hours to light-years.
从光时换到光年
A light-year is the yardstick of the cosmos.
光年是宇宙中的距离单位
A single one is nearly ten trillion kilometers,
1光年将近10万亿公里
or about six trillion miles.
大约6万亿英里
It's a unitive distance, just like a meter or a mile.
宇宙距离单位中  就像1米或1英里那样
It's the distance light travels in a year.
它是光线用1年时间可以穿越的距离长度
The nearest star to the Sun, Proxima Centauri,
离太阳最近的恒星  比邻星
is a little more than four light-years away from Earth.
离地球的距离超过4光年一点点
How far away is four light-years?
4光年有多远
NASA's Voyager spacecraft moves
NASA（美国国家航空航天局）的旅行者探测器
at more than 56,000 kilometers an hour.
速度超过每小时5万6千公里
Even at that astonishing speed, it would take Voyager
就算这么惊人的速度
more than 80,000 years to reach the nearest star.
也需要超过8万年  才能到达最近的恒星
And the stars of the Pleiades cluster,
昂宿星团（昴日星官大公鸡）的恒星
400 light-years away.
距离我们 400光年
The Ship of the Imagination
想象之舟
is equipped with a highly unusual capability--
有着一种不同寻常的能力
one-of-a-kind, actually.
独一无二的
It makes it possible for us
to see what was happening
它能让我们看到
when the light from a distant
star or galaxy first set out
光从遥远的恒星或星系发出
on its long journey to Earth.
直到地球的情形
♪ ♪
When that light left the Pleiades, about 400 years ago,
400年前  光从昴宿星团出发时
Galileo was taking his first look through a telescope.
伽利略首次使用望远镜
A few years later, he tried to
measure the speed of light,
几年后 他尝试测算光的速度
but he couldn't do it.
但是没有成功
He had a very clever plan,
but the technology of that era
他的计划很高明  可惜当时的科技
just wasn't good enough to
measure the motion of anything
还不能测量那么快的速度
that moves as fast as light.
像光那么快的速度
When we look at the Crab Nebula from Earth,
我们从地球上观察蟹状星云时
we're seeing much farther back in time.
我们看到的是更古老的过去
The Crab Nebula was once a giant star,
蟹状星云曾是一颗巨大的恒星
ten times the mass of the Sun,
质量比太阳大10倍
until it exploded in a supernova.
爆炸成为一颗超新星
At its heart is a pulsar,
它的中心是颗脉冲星
a collapsed star the size of a city,
城市般大小的一颗坍塌星 （中子星）
spinning 30 times a second.
每秒自转30次
This pulsar's whirling magnetic field
脉冲星的螺旋磁场
whips nearby electrons into a frenzy,
疯狂地卷动 周围的电子
accelerating them to almost the speed of light.
将它们加速到接近光的速度
They shine with a blue glow that
lights up the tendrils of gas
它们发出蓝色的光芒照亮超新星爆炸时
still unraveling from the supernova.
产生的气态卷须
The Crab Nebula
蟹状星云
is about 6,500 light-years from Earth.
距离地球大约6500光年
According to some beliefs,
在某些宗教信仰中
that's the age of the whole universe.
那是整个宇宙的年纪
But if the universe were only 6,500 years old,
但如果宇宙只有6500岁
how could we see the light from anything more distant
我们怎么可能看到更远的光
than the Crab Nebula?
比蟹状星云还远的光
We couldn't.
做不到
There wouldn't have been enough time for the light
那并没有足够的时间
to get to Earth from anywhere farther away
让光从距离
than 6,500 light-years in any direction.
超过6500光年的地方传来地球
That's just enough time for light to travel
那点时间只够光在
through a tiny portion of our Milky Way galaxy.
我们的银河系中穿越很短的距离
To believe in a universe
如果相信宇宙
as young as 6,000 or 7,000 years old
只有6千到7千岁
is to extinguish the light from most of the galaxy,
就是熄灭了银河系中大部分的光
not to mention the light from all the 100 billion
更别提那些可观测宇宙中
other galaxies in the observable universe.
上千亿星系发出的光
The center of our own galaxy
我们银河系的中心
is about 30,000 light-years from Earth.
距离地球大约3万光年
The light we see today
我们今天看到的光
coming from the core of the Milky Way left there...
从银河系的核心出发时
when our ancestors were perfecting a way
我们的远古祖先找到了
to vanquish death...
超越死亡的方法
by making art with the power
使用绘画的力量
to inspire those who would come
long after they were gone.
给予后世启示
♪ ♪
The light we see coming from the Sombrero Galaxy
从草帽星系传来的光
is 30 million years old.
走了3千万年
Our ancestors were living in trees when that light started out.
当光发出来时  我们的祖先还住在树上
They weighed about five kilos
and had long tails.
它们大约5公斤重  还有长长的尾巴
But even 30 million light-years away
但就算离我们3千万光年之外
is still in our own cosmic backyard.
从宇宙中看 也不过就在我们的后院
That galaxy is part of the Coma Cluster,
那个星系属于后发座星系团
320 million light-years away.
3亿2千万光年之遥
What was going on back home
当这里的光出发时
when the light you are seeing
began its trip to Earth?
当时的地球又是怎样的呢
No familiar continents, oceans or rivers.
没有我们熟悉的大陆  海洋  河流
Our distant ancestors were just
leaving the water for the land.
我们的远古祖先刚刚从水中登上陆地
That's pretty old light,
很古老的光
but not nearly the oldest light we can see.
但远不是 我们能看到的 最古老的光
The oldest light is very faint,
最古老的光已经很微弱了
a pale ghost in the night.
暗夜中虚弱的鬼魂
See that red blob inside the circle?
看到圆圈中的红点吗
That's one of the oldest
galaxies we've ever seen.
那是我们能见的最古老星系之一
You're looking at 13.4-billion year-old starlight
你看到的是134亿岁高龄的星光
as captured by the Hubble space telescope.
通过哈勃太空望远镜捕捉到的
It's coming from the very first generation of stars.
它来自第一代的星星
What was happening on Earth back then?
当时的地球什么情况
Absolutely nothing.
完全没情况
There was no Earth, no Sun, no Milky Way.
当时 没有地球 没有太阳 没有银河系
They would not come to be for billions of years.
它们都是几十亿后才诞生的
When we try to look even farther into the universe,
当我们看向宇宙的更深处
we come to what appears to be the end of space...
好像已经到了宇宙的尽头
but actually...
但 事实上
it's the beginning of time.
这是时间的开始
Earth pulls on us.
地球向下拉着我们
Our lives are a relentless struggle with gravity.
我们不断地反抗引力
That little girl is trying her best to climb out
这个小女孩用尽全力要爬出
of a gravitational well.
引力的包围
From our first efforts to stand to our final surrender,
从第一次尝试站立到最后的倒下
we are struggling to overcome the Earth's pull.
我们努力克服地心引力
We are born, live and die in a force field--
我们在重力场中诞生  生活  过世
one that is almost as old as the universe itself.
重力场几乎和宇宙本身一样的古老
And how old is that?
有多古老
To visualize the 13.8 billion year age of the universe,
为了想象宇宙的138亿年岁月
we've compressed all of cosmic time
我们把所有的宇宙时间
into a single year-at-a-glance calendar.
压缩在一份单张的年历中
Midnight on December 31 is this very moment right now.
现在就是12月31号的午夜
And January 1 is the beginning of time.
1月1号就是时间的开始
See that glowing fog out there?
看到那耀眼的烟雾吗
It's radiation left over from the Big Bang,
它是大爆炸遗留下的辐射物
the explosion that made the universe
大爆炸创造了宇宙
13.8 billion years ago.
138亿年前
Right now, we're at the very
edge of known space and time.
现在我们站在已知空间和时间的边缘
So what happened before the Big Bang?
大爆炸之前是什么样子
Nobody knows.
没人知道
No evidence survives from before that moment.
没有丝毫 关于那之前的证据
We've got some pretty crazy ideas
我们有一些很疯狂的猜想
about where the universe came from,
是关于宇宙的来源
which we'll get to, in time.
我们以后会提到
Where are we in the universe?
我们在宇宙的什么位置
At the very center.
就在正中心
In the observed universe,
everyone gets to feel special.
在已知宇宙中 每个人都觉得自己很特殊
No matter which galaxy you happen to live in,
不论你身处哪个星系
when you look out to the
universe, you'll find yourself
当你看向宇宙时  你会发现自己
at the center of the cosmic horizon.
身处宇宙地平线的中心
But this is just an illusion.
但这不过是个错觉
In reality, there is no center,
实际上  没有中心
and the cosmic horizon is no more real
宇宙地平线 和
than the horizon at sea.
海上的地平线 一样不真实
It's what you get when you have a finite speed of light
这是因为在 有起始时间的宇宙中
in a universe that had a beginning in time.
光速是有限的
A few hundred million years after the Big Bang,
大爆炸后的几亿年
vast clouds of hydrogen and helium condensed
大量的氢气和氦气云团
into the first stars and galaxies.
凝结成最初的恒星和星系
With these new sources of light,
有了这些新的光源
the long dark ages of the universe ended.
宇宙漫长的黑暗时代终结了
As space continued to expand,
随着宇宙的不断膨胀
cosmic evolution unfolded on grander scales.
宇宙进化的规模变得更加宏大
As the first generation of stars died,
最初的星星死亡
they seeded space with heavier elements,
它们将较重的元素散布在宇宙中
making possible the formation of planets,
使得行星的形成 成为可能
and ultimately, life.
最终 生命的形成
Matter and energy were formed in the Big Bang.
大爆炸形成了物质和能量
But that's not all.
还有
Space and time were created, too,
创造了空间和时间
and all the forces that bind matter together,
还有束缚所有物质的力量
including gravity.
包括 重力
Isaac Newton discovered a mathematical law
牛顿发现了一个数学定律
that describes how gravity works.
可以形容重力的运作机制
With that law, he could explain
the motions of the planets.
他可以用它解释行星间的运动
More than 100 years later,
100多年后
William Herschel realized gravity could do much more.
威廉·赫歇尔 意识到 那还不是全部
John, can you keep a secret?
约翰 你能保守秘密吗
Yes, Father.
可以 父亲
I've made a discovery and have
yet to tell another soul.
我有了一个发现  还没告诉过任何人
The gravity that holds us to the Earth--
地球上的地心引力
the same gravity that Newton showed
同样是牛顿发现的
keeps the planets in their orbits--
将行星保持在轨道上的引力
I've discovered
我发现
that it also rules the distant stars.
也同样适用于 相隔遥远的恒星们
Father... but how can you know this?
爹  你咋知道的
Can you find the constellation of the Lion?
你能找到狮子座吗
There.
在那
Well done.
干得好
Can you now find the star
你能找到
that joins the Lion's head to his body?
连接头部和身体的那颗星吗
That one.
那个
That star is really two stars
那其实是两颗星
so close together that they appear to be one.
靠的很近 看上去就像一颗
I've been watching them through my telescope
我用望远镜观察了很久
since long before you were born.
你出生很久前就开始了
They dance around each other very slowly.
它们非常缓慢的 围绕相互移动
More slowly than any planet moves around the Sun.
远比行星绕恒星运动的慢
Many of the stars we see tonight,
我们今晚看到的许多星星
perhaps most of them,
可能大部分
dance with invisible partners.
按照看不见的规律移动
Gravity's empire governs all the heavens.
万有引力这个大帝国统治着所有的星球
A century earlier,
1个世纪前
Isaac Newton had been haunted
艾萨克·牛顿备受困扰
by the same absence of a mechanism for gravity.
他也找不到引力的作用机制
How could distant bodies affect each other
相距甚远的物体 如何相互影响
across empty space without actually touching?
不用接触就相互影响
This "action at a distance,"
as he called it, baffled him.
这个他称之为 超距作用 的问题困扰着他
In the 19th century, Michael Faraday discovered
19世纪 迈克尔·法拉第（电学之父）发现
that we were surrounded by invisible fields of force
我们被不可见的力场包围
that explained how gravity works.
这解释了引力的运作机制
The apple and the Earth
don't touch each other,
苹果和地球 并没有发生接触
but the fields between them do.
但是它们之间的力场产生了接触
He imagined those lines of gravitational force
他想象引力产生的线
radiating out into space
from every massive body--
从每一个物体 向太空中辐射
the Earth, the Moon, the Sun, everything.
地球 月亮 太阳  所有的一切
Here was the answer to that question
这就是那个困扰牛顿的问题
that had stumped Newton.
的答案
In 1865, James Clerk Maxwell
translated Faraday's idea
1985年 詹姆斯·克拉克·麦克斯韦
about fields of electricity and magnetism
把法拉第关于电磁场的理论
into mathematical laws.
转化成了数学公式
He discovered that these fields
move through space in waves.
他发现这些磁场 电场都以波的形式在空间中移动
When he calculated how fast they move,
当他计算它们的移动速度时
it turned out to be the speed of light.
结果是 光的速度
We were beginning to discover the threads
我们才发现了  宇宙这个大挂毯上的线
of the cosmic tapestry,
but we were not yet able
to discern the rich pattern
但是我们还无法 看出丰富的图案
that time, light, space and gravity weave.
时间 光 空间 重力
As Albert Einstein worked in Berlin
阿尔伯特·爱因斯坦 在柏林
on his theory of gravity,
研究他的引力理论时
he kept the portraits of these three men before him.
墙上挂了这3位前辈的头像
He knew he was standing on their shoulders.
他知道他的成就  建立在他们的基础上
Years before, as a teenager, he had an insight
多年前  少年时  他有过一个顿悟
that was as Earth-shaking as any idea of theirs.
如同前辈们的理论那般惊天动地
And it happened one summer
那年夏天
while he was daydreaming in Italy.
他在意大利遐想时的顿悟
In the summer of 1895,
1895年的夏天
Einstein's father's business in Germany had failed,
他父亲在德国的生意失败
and the family had moved here to northern Italy.
全家搬到了意大利北部
Young Einstein loved wandering these roads
小爱因斯坦喜欢在这些路上散步
and giving his mind free rein to explore.
让他的思维随意发散
There's something timeless about this place.
这里有着某些永恒的东西
Nothing here has really changed
和爱因斯坦最初的遐想时相比
since the time of Einstein's early daydreams.
基本没什么变化
One day, he began to think about light
一天 他想到了光
and how fast it travels.
还有光速
In everyday life, we always measure the speed
日常生活中 我们总是测量物体
of a moving object with respect to something else.
相对于其他物体的移动速度
Something that's presumably not moving.
假设其他物体没有移动
Something in the cosmos that's not in motion.
宇宙中的其他物体没有运动
For example, I'm moving about ten kilometers per hour
比方说  我的速度大约每小时10公里
relative to the ground.
相对于地面而言
But as I mentioned earlier, the ground is moving.
但我之前提过  大地也在运动
Earth is turning at more than 1,600 kilometers per hour
地球的转速超过每小时1600公里
while it orbits the Sun
在环日轨道上
at more than 100,000 kilometers per hour.
速度超过每小时10万公里
And the Sun is moving through the galaxy
并且太阳系在银河系中运行
at a half a million miles per hour.
每小时50万英里（实际90万公里）的速度
And the Milky Way is moving through the universe
银河系在宇宙中运行
at nearly one and a half million miles an hour.
速度将近每小时150万英里（实际216万公里）
There is no fixed place in the cosmos.
宇宙中没有不动的地方
All of nature is in motion.
一切都在运动
It was hard even for the young Einstein
对小爱因斯坦来说  也是很难想象出
to imagine some absolute standard
一个绝对的标准
to measure all those relative motions against.
用来衡量所有这些相对的运动
This is the very book
就是这本书
that inspired Einstein as a young boy.
启发了少年爱因斯坦
Give a kid a book and you change the world.
给了他一本书  改变了这个世界
In a way, even the universe.
某种程度上  改变了这个宇宙
Look at this-- the very first page,
看这里  第一页
it describes the astonishing speed
它描述了令人惊讶的
of electricity through wires
电流通过电线的速度
and light through space.
光穿过宇宙的速度
Einstein remembered what he'd learned as a child
from this book
爱因斯坦记得他小时候从这本书里学到的
and perhaps, for the first time, right here,
或许 最初 就在这里
wondered what the world would look like
想象着这个世界将会如何
if you could travel at the speed of light.
如果可以用光速运动
The more Einstein thought about it,
爱因斯坦越想
the more troubled he became.
越觉得困惑
If you imagine traveling at the speed of light,
如果你想象以光速运动
paradoxes seem to pop up everywhere.
各个方面都充满了矛盾
Einstein was shocked to realize that so much
爱因斯坦惊讶的发现 如此众多的
of what had been uncritically accepted as truth
即使是被最伟大的权威人士
by even the greatest authorities on the subject
无条件接受的真理
was just plain wrong.
竟是大错特错
When traveling at high speeds,
以高速运动时
there are certain rules which must be obeyed.
必须遵守一些特定的规则
Einstein called these rules "The Principles of Relativity."
爱因斯坦称之为 相对性原理
Imagine that young woman who just blew past us
想象刚才那位呼啸而过
on the motorbike,
骑摩托的年轻女士
imagine she was riding her bike
想象她骑车穿行
through the cosmos.
在宇宙中
Light from a moving object travels
从移动的物体上发出的光
at the same speed, no matter whether the object
不论物体是静止还是移动
is at rest or in motion.
速度都是一样的
Her speed is not added to the speed of light.
她的速度并不会增加光的速度
The light from her motorbike
从她的摩托车发出的光
still travels at the speed of light.
依然是光的速度
Nature commands,
大自然的谕旨
"Thou shalt not add my speed to the speed of light."
汝不可超越光速
Also, no material object
同样 没有物质
can travel at or faster than the speed of light.
传播速度可以达到或者超过光速
There's nothing in physics that prevents you
物理上 没有什么可以阻止你
from traveling as close to the speed of light as you like.
随心所欲地接近光的速度
99.9% of the speed of light is just fine,
99.9%的光速 没问题
but no matter how hard you try,
但是无论你怎么努力
you never gain that last decimal point.
都无法得到 最后的那个百分点
For reality to be logically consistent,
以现实的逻辑一致性来说
there must be a cosmic speed limit.
必然存在一个宇宙速度极限
The crack of that whip is due to its tip
鞭子发出的声音是因为
moving faster than the speed of sound.
鞭头的移动速度超过了声速
It makes a shockwave,
产生了冲击波
a mini sonic boom,
in the Italian countryside.
在意大利乡村的  一个小小的音爆
A thunderclap works the same way,
打雷也是一样的道理
and so does the sound of a passing supersonic jet.
还有超音速飞机掠过时的声音
So why is the speed of light
那为什么光速
any more a barrier than the speed of sound?
比音速更难超越
The answer is not just that light travels
答案是 不仅仅光速
about a million times faster than sound.
比音速快100万倍
And it's not merely an engineering problem,
也因为 这不仅是一个工程学问题
like building the first supersonic jet.
像建造首架超音速飞机那种
Instead, the light barrier
光障
is a fundamental law of nature,
是自然的基本定律
as basic as gravity.
就像万有引力一样基本
Einstein found his absolute framework for the world,
爱因斯坦为这个世界设定了绝对的准则
this sturdy pillar among all the relative motions
这给了宇宙运动中的
within the motions of the cosmos.
所有相对运动强有力的支持
Light travels just as fast,
光速就是那么快
no matter how fast or slow its source is moving.
无论光源移动的快慢
Speed of light is constant, relative to everything else.
相对其他任何东西 光速是恒定的
Nothing can ever catch up with light.
没有什么可以追上光
The thing about the laws of nature
自然定律的伟大就是在于
is that they're unbreakable.
它们无懈可击
The job of physicists is to discover these commandments,
物理学家的工作就是发现这些定律
the ones that do not vary from culture to culture
定律不随文化的不同而改变
or time to time
也不随时间而改变
and hold true throughout the cosmos.
放之宇宙而皆准
That's why, as Einstein showed,
这就是为何  如同爱因斯坦指出的
funny things happen close to the speed of light.
接近光速时就出问题了
Traveling close to the speed of light
以接近光速的速度旅行
is kind of an elixir of life
就像是长生不老药
because your biological clock slows down
我们的生物钟慢下来
relative to those you leave behind.
相对于其他人来说
This phenomenon may provide us humans,
这种现象或许可以为我们人类
who only live for a century or so,
只能活1个世纪左右的人类
a practical means to travel to the stars,
提供一个可行的恒星间旅行的方案
where the magic show of spacetime
时空魔法大戏
really gets crazy.
精彩纷呈
The 19th-century astronomer William Herschel
19世纪的天文学家 威廉·赫歇尔
loved to share the wonders of the universe
喜欢和他的儿子约翰 分享
with his son John.
宇宙中的奇迹
I once had a friend, very clever fellow,
我有个朋友  很聪明的家伙
an astronomer and a parson at Leeds,
天文学家 也是里兹的牧师
by the name of John Michell.
名叫 约翰·米切尔
Poor man died when you were a babe,
你还是婴儿时 他就过世了
God rest his soul.
愿他安息
He held that some stars
他相信有些星星
are invisible.
虽然看不到
They really exist,
but we shall never see them.
却确实存在 但是我们永远无法看到
"Dark stars," Michell called them.
米切尔叫它们 暗星
With all due respect, Father,
恕我直言 父亲
surely your friend was mistaken.
你的朋友肯定弄错了
If no one can see them,
如果没人能看到
then how can we possibly know they exist?
我们怎么能知道它们确实存在
Did you see the man
who left those footprints, John?
你看到留下脚印的人了吗
Why, no, Father.
没 怎么了
I did not.
我没看到
But do you know that he exists?
但你知道他们确实存在
John Michell is one of the greatest scientists
约翰·米切尔是最伟大的科学家之一
you've probably never heard of.
你可能从没听说过
He lived and worked in England in the 18th century.
他生活工作于18世纪的英格兰
If he ever sat for a portrait, it no longer exists.
现在也没有他的画像存世
He was once described by an acquaintance
有人曾经形容他
as "a short little man,
胖胖的黝黑小矮人
of black complexion, and fat."
Michell imagined a star so big,
米切尔设想一个巨大的恒星
so massive, that nothing, not even light,
质量巨大到 即使光线
could escape its gravitational grip.
也无法逃离它的重力吸引
Can you find the dark star?
你能找到暗星吗
You can't see it with your eyes, not directly,
你无法用肉眼直接看见它
but it may leave a kind of footprint
但它可能留下某种足迹
on the cosmic shore.
在宇宙这个沙滩上
Michell realized that we might be able to detect
米切尔认为我们或许可以侦测到
some of these dark stars because of their extreme gravity.
某些暗星 因为它们巨大的引力
If one happened to be near
如果一个暗星 碰巧伴随着一个
a smaller, luminous companion star,
稍小些 会发光的星星
that star would appear to travel in a tight orbit
那颗星星以紧密的轨道
around nothing.
环绕着 看不见的东西运行
Even though we can't see it,
即使我们看不到
we know something with a lot of mass
我们也知道 有个质量超级巨大的
has to be right there.
东西在那里
A dark star,
暗星
or what today we call a black hole.
或者叫 黑洞
What does a black hole look like
黑洞长什么样子
and what would it be like inside?
它的里面是什么样子的
We'll get there, but first,
我们以后会提到  但是首先
let's make a pit stop in my hometown,
我们在我的家乡稍作休息
New York City,
纽约
where it's always seemed to me
这地方在我来看
that everything is in constant motion.
所有的一切都在不停的运动
I've lived here most of my life.
我在这里住了大半辈子
There's always something new to see.
总有新鲜事物
But one thing never changes-- gravity.
但有一样从来不变 重力
Gravity on Earth has been the same
重力在过去的45亿年间
for the past four and a half billion years.
一直保持不变
But what if, today, we could alter it?
如果 今天 我们可以改变它
Gravity is a distortion
重力受时空影响
in the shape of spacetime
会发生畸变
as Einstein showed.
如同爱因斯坦提出的理论
Space can expand and contract
空间可以膨胀和收缩
and warp without limit.
无限弯曲
If the Earth's size or density
如果地球的体积和密度
were even a little different,
有细微的不同
its gravity would be, too.
它的重力也会不同
There's an infinite range of possibilities.
有无限的可能性
New Yorkers feel right at home
纽约人在这里感受到的
in the gravitational pull of the Earth,
重力单位
called "one g."
我们称为 1g
Suppose we turn off the gravity on one of its streets.
假设我们取消一条街上的重力
People and objects that were already in motion
运动中的人和物体
are launched into flight.
就会向上飞去
Now what if I turn the gravity up
如果我把重力加大到
to, say, eight or nine g's?
比方说 8或者9g
Out of compassion,
和谐起见
let's evacuate the area.
把人拿开
This is about the same g-force
这个重力和战斗机飞行员
that a fighter pilot in a high-speed turn would feel.
高速转弯时承受的重力相当
A few minutes of this wouldn't hurt you,
几分钟内 还不会使你受伤
but it wouldn't be comfortable.
但是绝不会舒服
At 100,000 g's,
在10万g时
even fire hydrants become crushed
消防栓也被自身的重量
by their own enormous weight.
压扁了
But at millions of g's,
几百万g
even light bows to gravity.
光线也会被拉弯
The light still moves at its constant speed,
光线依然保持恒速
but it cannot escape.
但它无法逃逸
Michell's dark star...
米切尔说的暗星
our black hole.
我们称为黑洞
And the nearest one may be closer than you think.
最近的一个 或许比想象的要近
Not every star can become a black hole.
不是每个恒星都会变成黑洞
Only about one in a thousand is massive enough.
只有千分之一的质量足够大
The nearest one could be within 100 light years of Earth.
最近的一个 可能距离地球不到100光年
Black holes aren't the mythic cosmic
vacuum cleaners of science fiction.
黑洞不是科幻小说里的宇宙吸尘器
They don't go around gobbling up
unsuspecting worlds.
它们不会到处吞噬
You've got to come to them.
你得去找它们
But if you do,
但是如果你去了
it might be the last thing you ever see.
可就是有去无回
That was us resisting a few million g's of gravity.
刚才那是我们在抵抗上百万g的重力
Don't forget, that thing swallows light.
别忘了 那家伙可以吞噬光线
We'll keep our distance.
我们不能靠的太近
When giant stars exhaust their nuclear fuel,
当巨大的恒星消耗完它们的核燃料
they can no longer stay hot enough
它们不再保持高温
to fend off the inward pull of their own gravity.
以抵消自身向内的引力
The most massive stars collapse into darkness,
质量最大的恒星塌陷
leaving only their gravity behind.
没有光亮 只留下重力
This black hole enshrouds
the shrunken corpse
这个黑洞将一个超巨星的萎缩的尸体
of a supergiant star.
隐藏其中
The star itself has shriveled into something
恒星本身可能萎缩到
even smaller than this darkness,
比黑洞还小
only 64 kilometers wide.
只有64公里宽
This is the first black hole ever discovered--
这是发现的第一个黑洞
Cygnus X-1.
天鹅座X-1
How did we on Earth ever find something
我们在地球上是怎么发现
so small and dark and far away?
这么小 这么暗 这么远的 东西
We looked at it in another kind of light. X-rays.
我们通过另一种光 X光
In X-ray light, we lost sight of the blue star
X光中 我们看不到蓝色的星星了
because its surface is a tepid 30,000 degrees.
因为它的表面温度只有微温的3万度
But the disk of gas around the black hole
而黑洞周围的气体圆盘
glowed brilliantly in X-rays at 100 million degrees.
在X光中发出耀眼的光芒 温度高达1亿度
As William Herschel discovered,
如同威廉·赫歇尔所发现的
many stars have close companions
forming a binary star system.
很多恒星都有亲密的小伙伴  组成联星系统
But if one member of such a pair is enormous
但如果其中一个异常巨大
and the other is compact,
另一个比较小
the smaller star can drain
and consume the atmosphere
小的这个可以吞噬它兄弟的
of its larger sibling.
大气层
This neurotic relationship
can last for millions of years.
这种神经病关系可以持续几百万年
The atmosphere of the larger star was being siphoned onto
较大恒星的大气层被抽到炽热耀眼的吸积盘上
a glowing hot accretion disk that revolves around
吸积盘不停自转
and spirals into a black hole.
并且漩涡式的进入黑洞
The overwhelming gravity was
accelerating the blue star's gas
势不可挡的重力不断加速蓝色星星的气体
into a death spiral,
将其卷入死亡漩涡
crossing the spacetime boundary,
跨过时空的界限
never to be seen again.
一去不复返
The fateful boundary that separates a black hole
这至关重要的界限将黑洞
from the rest of the universe is called an event horizon.
与宇宙的其他部分隔离开  被称为 事件视界
From our point of view, the substance in the disk
在我们看来 吸积盘中的物质
slows down as it approaches the event horizon,
在靠近视界时慢下来
never quite reaching it.
但绝不接触它
But if you were riding on that spiraling gas--
如果你站在大气漩涡上
and I don't advise it--
我并不建议这么做
you would sail past the event horizon in a matter of seconds
几秒钟就会越过事件视界
into the undiscovered country from which no traveler returns.
进入到 从没人回来的 未知国度
We have searched the hearts of dozens of galaxies,
我们搜索了几十个星系的中心
and in every case, we have found
a super-massive black hole.
在每个里面都能找到 一个质量超级大的黑洞
Our own galaxy is no exception.
我们的银河系也不例外
The stars nearest the center
of our galaxy whip around
最靠近银河系中心的恒星运动的速度
at more than 40 million kilometers an hour.
超过每小时4千万公里
What could make them move so fast?
它们怎么会运动的这么快
The only logical explanation
唯一合理的解释是
is that something with the mass
银河系中央存在着
of four million suns lies at the center.
质量等于4百万个太阳的物体
So where's the blazing light of four million suns?
这4百万个太阳发出的光去哪里了
Since we can't see it,
既然我们看不见
it must be imprisoned inside a black hole.
它一定是被禁锢在黑洞里了
Earth is far enough away to be perfectly safe.
地球离得很远 很安全
Other worlds might not be so lucky.
其他的世界或许没有这么幸运
If you somehow survived the perilous journey
如果你能穿过事件视界
across the event horizon,
却还活着
you'd be able to look back out
你可以回头看
and see the entire future history of the universe
宇宙的整部未来史都会
unfold before your eyes.
展现在你眼前
How?
怎么会的
Because when spacetime is warped
因为 时空受到
by the extreme gravity of a black hole,
黑洞的极度重力影响而扭曲
time is stretched to the limit.
时间被拉伸至极致
But what would be in front of you?
但你面前会是何种景象呢
Before we go there, I should warn you
我提前警告你
that we're entering uncharted scientific territory.
我们说的是未经涉足过的科学领域
For all we know, there may be
undiscovered laws of physics
那里可能有我们未知的物理定律
that govern events at the center of a black hole.
支配着黑洞中央的事情
But until the next Einstein comes along,
在下一个爱因斯坦出现前
let's perform a thought experiment.
我们来做个思想实验吧
That's how John Michell first imagined dark stars
18世纪的约翰 米切尔
in the 18th century,
就是靠它想象出 暗星
and how Einstein conceived of his theory of rela...
爱因斯坦也是这么想出他的...
Father, do you believe in ghosts?
父亲 你相信有鬼魂吗
Oh, no, not in the human kind of ghosts.
我不信有 人类的鬼魂
No, not at all.
完全不信
But look up, my boy,
但是 向上看 儿子
and see a sky full of them.
满天都是鬼魂
If you could survive the trip into a black hole,
你如果去过黑洞还能活着回来
you might emerge in another place
你可能会发现
and time in our own universe,
我们宇宙中的其他时间和空间
circumventing the first commandment of relativity...
先不提 相对论的第一条戒律
thou shalt not travel faster than light.
汝不可超越光速
Nothing can move through space faster than light.
太空中没有什么速度可以比光速快
But space is not mere emptiness.
但太空并不空旷
Its properties can stretch
and shrink and can be deformed.
空间可以延伸 收缩  被扭曲
And when that happens, time is deformed, too.
那样的话 时间也会被扭曲
Einstein discovered that spaceand time are just two aspects
爱因斯坦发现 空间和时间 只是
of the same thing, spacetime.
一个事物的两个方面  时空
Spacetime itself can deform enough
时空本身可以被任意弯曲
to carry you anywhere at any speed.
用任意速度带你去任意地方
Black holes may very well be tunnels
through the universe.
黑洞可能是不同宇宙间的隧道
On this intergalactic subway
system, you could travel
通过这种星际间的交通系统 你可以
to the farthest reaches of spacetime,
达到时空的最远端
or you might arrive in someplace even more amazing.
或许其他更惊人的地方
We might find ourselves in an
altogether different universe.
或许是个完全不一样的宇宙
But how can a whole universe fit
inside of a black hole,
但是一个黑洞怎么能容纳整个宇宙
which is only a small part of our universe?
黑洞只是我们宇宙中的很小一部分
It's another magic trick of spacetime.
这又是一个时空变出的戏法
The phenomenal gravity of a black hole
黑洞无与伦比的引力
can warp the space of an entire universe inside it.
可以将整个宇宙的空间扭曲并塞进去
Our local gravity might be a drag to us,
我们现在受到的引力 或许很强
but it's really feeble compared
但却无法和
with what goes on inside a collapsed star.
萎缩恒星内部的引力 相提并论
As far as we know,
据我们所知
when a giant star collapses
to make a black hole,
当超大恒星萎缩成黑洞时
the extreme density and pressure at the center
中心产生极大的密度和压力
mimic the Big Bang, which gave rise to our universe.
如同诞生宇宙的大爆炸
And a universe inside a black hole
于是黑洞内诞生了一个宇宙
might give rise to its own black holes.
这宇宙可能会产生它自己的黑洞
And those could lead to other universes.
这些黑洞 又会产生其他的宇宙
Maybe that's how our cosmos came to be.
或许我们的宇宙就是如此
For all we know,
众所周知
if you want to see what it's like inside a black hole,
如果你想知道黑洞里面有什么
just look around you.
只要看看四周
William Herschel went on to discover that the sun
威廉·赫歇尔发现了 太阳
and its planets are moving through the Milky Way.
带着它的行星们 在银河系中运行
And whatever became of his son John?
他的儿子有什么成就呢
He grew up to become a great scientist.
他成为了一位伟大的科学家
His deep-space observations built on those of his father
在他父亲的基础上 他所得出的外太空观测结果
to become the basis for the standard catalog of galaxies
成为了星系标准目录的依据
we use today.
沿用至今
When William was in failing health, John stayed with him
当威廉身体不好时  约翰陪着他
through the long nights at his telescope
在望远镜旁 度过长夜
to help him sweep the stars.
帮他观测恒星
And when his father died, John wrote his epitaph...
父亲过世后 约翰写下墓志铭
"He broke through the walls of heaven."
他推倒天堂的围墙
John often reminisced
约翰经常缅怀
about those summer nights with his father.
与他父亲度过的那些夏日夜晚
Maybe that's why he sought a way to preserve the past.
这或许就是为何 他要寻找保存过去的方法
John Herschel was one of the founders
约翰·赫歇尔 是一种展现形式的时间旅行的
of a new form of time travel,
创始人之一
a means to capture light and memories.
一种保留光线和记忆的办法
He actually coined a word for it,
他为它选择了一个名字
photography.
摄影
When you think about it,
你这么想
photography is a form of time travel.
摄影是时间旅行的一种形式
This man is staring at us from across the centuries...
几百年前的人注视着我们
a ghost preserved by light.
光线勾勒出的鬼魂
It's not hard to imagine that in the near future,
不难想象 在不远的未来
we'll be able to capture the past
我们可以保留过去
in all three dimensions.
以三维立体的形式
We'll be able to step inside a memory.
我们可以走进一段记忆
It may not be possible to travel backward in time,
或许不能回到过去的时间
but perhaps, one day, we can bring the past to us.
但可能 有一天 可以将过去带来现在
Here's a moment from my past.
这是我过去的一刻
Like John Herschel,
就像约翰·赫歇尔
I'm remembering a younger version of myself.
我记得幼年的我
December 20, 1975.
1975年12月20号
A snowy day in Ithaca, New York.
纽约的一个雪天
A branchpoint on the road that brought me
生命旅程的一个拐点
to this moment with you.
让我有机会站在这里
It was the day I met Carl Sagan.
那天我遇到了卡尔·萨根
Reminds me of those ghost stars in the sky...
就如同天空中那些星星的鬼魂
you know, the ones that still shine their light upon us
long after they're gone.
即使已经消亡 但星光依然照耀我们
Sync and corrections by n17t01
www.addic7ed.com
中文翻译：@SaltyEggPain